We are at a moment where it's
essentially very dangerous that we lose
control as humans.
>> This is Martin Oderski, the creator of
Scola, and I asked him all about
programming languages and how they're
going to change in the future.
>> I believe right now Rust is actually
overused. So Zik is I believe is much
better because the the inlining
mechanism is much ser. This pisses off
both communities and they're promptly
declared jihad. If the code is AI
generated, then the focus has to go
elsewhere. And I think the focus will go
to the interfaces and to the types.
>> 10 [snorts] years from now, do you think
there will be more software engineers
than today or less? Here's the full
episode.
What is functional programming and why
should an imperative programmer care
about the functional way of programming?
So functional programming is programming
with values. Uh so you don't have state
that changes like mutable variables that
change or arrays that change. You have
values and you have functions and the
functions transform these values into
other values. So it's a very restricted
form of programming and most real
functional programming languages uh are
impure in the sense that yes of course
at some point you have to touch state
and change things and write to standard
out and things like that but the idea is
to do that sort of uh very late. So to
have the largest part of your program
represented as values and functions that
transform values and the benefit you get
from that is essentially much better
predictability and fewer bugs because
these side effects to let's say a global
variable or a field in some object graph
or things like that they can really uh
trip you up. Uh they can they can
essentially they're an undocumented
effect of your function. So it's not
reflected anywhere typically but may
maybe you have a comment if if things
are good uh and and these things are
very hard to keep in your head and
generally reason about. So the advice
from functional programming is
essentially to keep these things to the
bare minimum and possibly to nothing if
your function maps into these things. Um
the other reason why function
programming is nice is that it's very
directly linked to mathematics. Uh so in
mathematics you have theories of let's
say polomials or strings or lists or
things like that. And in none of these
theories you will find the concept of
mutation. It just doesn't exist. So you
can take a polomial and you can
transform it into a new polomial but you
can't change a coefficient coefficient
at 3 at the third coefficient and
pretend it's the same polomial. It's not
in mathematics, right? It's clearly
something different. So functional
programming you could say follows quite
closely the way mathematics sees things.
>> What would you say to someone that
doesn't do functional programming
because it's not convenient? I
>> I guess two things. one is uh uh it's
it's a learning uh uh curve. Uh so
initially you you're sort of your brain
is wired to be to do imperative
programming from when you were very
young. I imagine most people learned an
imperative language first and then it's
hard to see how you would express things
differently.
uh but if you persist in that a little
bit and it doesn't really take much then
you will essentially reap the benefits
very quickly that you say well I
actually my program got a lot clearer I
can understand it better uh I don't
really have to track uh some uh steps go
step by step through through my program
with a debugger or things like that to
to figure out what it does typically I
don't need a debugger when I write
functional code that that's really not
not uh not not necessary
u the The other thing is to essentially
know when to stop. So uh there is a
strand of functional programming called
pure function programming which tries to
express as much as possible in pure
functions and to sort of delay the side
effects uh to and wrap them up in monuts
or whatnot and that can get very
inconvenient very quickly. Uh so uh the
my answer to that would be it really
depends and in most cases it's
completely okay to have your side
effects as long as these are well
documented and and you you you use them.
So basically use these things in
moderation. I would say functional
programming is great for 95% of your
program and if you need some side effect
some imperative uh feature for the last
5% that's also okay. Is there any
quantitative measure of the um I guess
the correctness benefits that functional
programming gives you over imperative?
>> Um I I think there are some studies. Uh
it's not quite clear how significant
they are. I think people criticize them
a lot. The [snorts] studies tend to say
that a language like Scala would have
fewer bucks than a language like C or
C++. But uh I don't really want to sort
of insist on that because these studies
are very hard to do and the methodology
is very hard to get right. I believe the
effects come uh are uh become more
important in large programs than in
small ones. For small ones you can do
anything really. You can write it with
you can write a loop, you can write a
recursive function. It doesn't really
matter and it's [snorts] it's very much
a matter of taste which one you prefer.
But in a large system I believe so I
believe that let's say static types have
certainly proven their worth and even
that we don't really have a conclusive
study that shows it. I mean I can point
you to a study and if you're a dynamic
typing enthusiast and you can point you
will point to another that essentially
claims the opposite. So it's very very
hard to do empirical software
engineering on that scale. Um and uh so
I'm afraid I I can't really give a good
answer. I just have the feeling that
mostly functional statically typed
languages is sort of a sweet spot for
for getting programs right. Maybe the
other thing is when you really need to
get them absolutely right like with with
proofs and things like that. Uh if you
do rock or lean or any of these things
these are all functional languages. So
people wouldn't wouldn't even attempt to
do something like C C++ here. When you
think about Scola in the environment of
all programming languages, what sets
Scola apart? Or maybe put in another
way, why should someone learn Scola in
2026?
>> Well, Scala is the only functional
language that is also a very capable
object-oriented language. In fact, it
was born uh by the idea that we can
actually make a fusion of the two in a
way which is not a side by side but
which really combines the features in a
in a nice synthesis. So that was what
what Scala was about. That's what I
wanted to show and I think that's been
largely successful. So you can write
really beautiful programs in this
combination. uh object-oriented
programming comes in when you talk about
components and modules and uh
essentially encapsulation these sort of
things where functional programming
typically doesn't really have a very
strong story. I mean there are languages
like standard ML or or camel that do
have very capable module systems but
other functional languages don't and and
people when they think of functional
programming they don't really think much
about components and interfaces and
these sort of things which are things
that I believe also matter very much.
>> Could you give an example maybe um like
an object-oriented thing that you could
do in Scola but you couldn't do in
Haskell which is pure functional. it's
sort of ingrained. It's in the whole
fabric of the things that everything is
essentially objects what what you do. Um
so so one thing that you get is what I
think Simon Pton Jones called the power
of the dot uh that you say it's super
convenient. You have an object and then
you do dot and then you have the
environment that immediately tells you
what are the methods and fields of that
object that they can use them. So it
focuses your mind. Whereas in function
programming, it's typically you have a
sea of functions that can uh be be
applied to arguments and you have to
figure out what they are.
>> When you think about the systems
programming languages like Rust, Zigg,
Go, C, C++, uh in your opinion, which
one would you say is kind of the best
one and then maybe we can compare it to
Scala?
>> In this day and age, a systems
programming languages needs to be memory
safe, guaranteed memory safe. So that
would already exclude quite a few of
them but it would leave Rust and Go I
think and Rust and Go are at different
levels. Go is really not not a sort of a
nuts and bolt systems programming
languages is more language in which you
would write let's say an application
server or some middleware or some cloud
infrastructure or things like that. It's
not something you would use for embedded
say which which you would would use Rust
for. So I think in their domain both of
them are are probably the ones that that
are the leading ones that I would take
most seriously.
>> And then when you compare you know Rust
or Go with Scola what are the pros and
cons of the different language designs?
What's something that Rust does better
than Scala? Something that Scola does
better than Rust
>> so Rust is closer to the metal. you have
better performance guarantees I guess uh
the fact that Scala is a garbage
collected language means that you always
have some pauses I mean garbage
collection colle collectors have become
quite quite capable I mean they're
brilliant and the pauses are really very
very small but it's fact it's it's a
fact that you do need a big chunk of
memory to run fast and I guess Rust
could could run in much much smaller
memory so I believe that's that's better
for embedded systems and things like
that. I believe right now rust is
actually overused because a lot of
people push sort of rush rust for things
higher higher up in the stack where you
garbage collector is fine but uh
essentially you you still want to write
code without and that is for me a bit an
exercise in
uh I don't know just intellectual that I
can do it I I don't think really think
there's a there's a big sense in it that
if you have the memory for a garbage
collector, you should absolutely use one
because it makes a lot of things uh
simpler. So yes, of course, if given
enough uh brains, I can write code
around and I can do that. But why should
you? I mean, it it it can be much
simpler.
So that was for Rust. Uh for Go, go is
um sort of a language a bit that that
lags behind. I mean was intentionally
designed to be to be very very small and
essentially to be the standards of the
languages in the '9s. U so now they have
gotten generics which is a big step. So
I believe that sort of is sort of a step
forward for that but it's still a fairly
limited language what you can do which
has an advantage that essentially it is
forces a very uniform style because
there's not much of different things you
can do and that's probably it a culture
fostered to do things in a certain way
which makes it easier to essentially
read one's other's programs and and
essentially jump in a new code base and
things like that. So I think that would
be my main advantage of go that I see
there.
>> Is it possible to turn off the garbage
collector in Scola?
>> Not in production. Uh so we have some
research that uh would let you use
essentially your own memory allocators
and things like that. Uh uh the the way
let's say Zigg does it. The problem with
that is always that you uh you you can
leak references into memory that you
reclaim and then all hell breaks use
lose essentially your your pointers
point to memory that's undefined and and
so but in in Scala we we now have a very
good way to actually track these
references so we can actually prevent
that statically by the type system that
this will never happen and you can still
have your own allocator. That said, we
haven't really shipped that in
production yet. So, right now, I would
say you use the garbage collector,
escala. Yeah,
>> I see uh a lot on the internet people
comparing Rust and Zigg or kind of a
fierce debate on which one is better.
When you think about Rust versus Zigg,
what are the merits of the two compared
comparing to each other? So what I can
see is Zik has a really nifty uh compile
time uh uh uh construct uh essentially
inlining where the compiler does smart
inlining and and and that is quite clean
and quite powerful and Rust has has
macros but I think they're more clunky
than there is than the zik version. Um
in Scala we have something quite close
to zik. We also have essentially very a
thing that's based on on inlining and
optimizations by the compiler. Uh but we
have a restriction which I believe sik
doesn't have and that is that um there
cannot be additional type errors after
inlining. So the thing is you inline and
then the question is is the inline
program guaranteed correct uh so type
correct or might you have type errors?
The typical example where you might have
type errors is C++ templates. In fact,
that's quite quite scary in C++ that you
can expand a template and then you get
very very complex type errors and very
very hard to to to debug things. So, ZIK
is I believe is much better because the
the inlining mechanism is much ser.
>> When you say inlining, can you explain
the concept? Inlining just means that uh
in in Scala we can write inline in front
of a of a function and that means that
the compiler will uh before it starts
code generating. So during the time when
it looks at the type code which are
trees it will take the function body
when it sees a function call to that
function it will take the call and
replace it by the body and then it will
do some optimizations. it can say okay
so here we have essentially an app an
application to let's say a value which
is a lambda and but I know where the
lambda points to so let me forward the
call right to the function uh so and and
with that you can already do quite a bit
of uh essentially optimizations which
are guaranteed because the the inliner
must inline that's that's not a thing
like an optimizer has essentially
discretion whether they want to inline
things or not and so you can never rely
on that but an an inliner which is uh
essentially a compile time based on the
typer must inline so you can rely on it
and const explore by in in zik and C++
is essentially very similar
>> okay so it's a way to get rid of the
function call or the overhead of a
function call and tell the compiler you
can do more because it's all I guess
inline
>> yeah you reveal the implementation and
That means you you can you can uh the
compiler can do something with that.
>> When you think about all the dynamically
typed languages, um which one stands out
as one that you think is kind of the
best among them?
>> Python is ubiquitous. Um and it has a
nice syntax. It uh a lot of the Python
programs look like they're very easy to
read. So that's definitely an advantage.
and and the other one would probably be
something like scheme uh which is sort
of very grounded in computer science
theory and lambda calculus and things
like that. So both of them are sort of
interesting in their own way but of
course Python is 100 times more popular.
>> If you compare Scola to Python for
instance I guess what are the trade-offs
that the two languages took? I think the
gap is closing because Python now
actually has an optional type syntax and
a number of type checkers that check
that syntax in Python is getting some of
the features that Scala had since the
beginning like pattern matching is in
one of the the recent Pythons. So I
think actually the gap is closing not
just between Python and Scala but but
between a lot of programming languages
in general there sort of all drift to a
standard set of features which mostly
come from functional programming
actually pattern matching for instance
strong type systems uh generics
polymorphism all these things came from
closures all these things came from
functional programming and so the gap is
closing in that in that sense um Python
is um I think the main advantage of
Scala over Python is that it is it has a
strong type system that is always on and
that gives you essentially guarantees uh
that essentially certain bad states
can't can't can't happen. So, so you
really can rely on it. Whereas I think I
believe the Python type system, well,
it's just syntax. It has a number of
type checkers, but in general there's
there's le you you have fewer guarantees
and I believe it's also the ecosystem
and culture that doesn't value types as
much in Python. So, I think that's
probably the main difference.
Fantactically, the two languages I think
with Scala 3 are actually also quite
close. So, Scala 3 looks a lot like
Python. Um, in that sense, uh, you could
say well can see it as a
as a language that has strong types and,
uh, runs on on different runtimes than
Python. Or I should say the other thing
with Python which is really great is
that Python is a fantastic glue language
because I can essentially have very very
efficient linkages to to high
performance C++ libraries. uh uh pandas
or numpy or things like that.
>> You mentioned that a lot of the
programming languages they're kind of uh
drifting or kind of being inspired by
the other ones and you know adopting new
features in the design of Scola. Is
there a programming language that you
admire most and influences Scola the
most? Historically, Scala was
essentially you could say it was a blend
of Java,
Okamel and or standard ML which is close
an [snorts] MLike language and and
Haskell. Uh so I I I I'm by trade well
I'm by trade an imperative program. My
PhD is from Nicholas W. So I know
Pascal, modular that was sort of my
first generation of languages and I
liked them a lot and then I became sort
of a converted functional programmer. So
I I looked very closely at ML, Okl,
Haskell and these things and then um the
Scala came about sort of there was a
predecessor language called pizza and I
was working on that with Phil Wadler
who's one of the Haskell original
designers and the idea was to have
essentially an accessible functional
language on a very widespread platform
which was a JVM at that at that point
and um the uh in order to prepare for
that I wrote a Java compiler. So that's
how I learned a lot about Java and what
Java was. And in the end I I had had to
say well it's actually quite useful. I I
I was quite dismissive at first but
afterwards I found it actually quite
useful. I mean this was very early Java.
This was Java even pre 1.0. So so now
Java is is of course even more useful
but also a lot bigger than what it was
at the time. Um so when we came up with
with Scala which was sort of the second
iteration after pizza, pizza was the
language I did with Phil water. Uh the
the
ideas came mostly from Java uh Okamel
for the modules and the component module
and Haskell a lot for the standard
libraries. So if you look at the
function names of the in the Scala
standard library then there's sort of a
mixture of Okamel and Haskell you could
say but you you recognize a lot of
things coming from both of these these
languages
>> if I recall correctly uh Java was had
some sort of licensing with it or was
owned by a company. Um how were you able
to build on top of Java or did you have
to pay for licenses or how how' that
ecosystem work? the language standard
was open source. Um there were there was
a lot of experimentation with Java at
the time. Um I think the only thing that
Sun was that was the company at the time
they're very particular about is that
you absolutely if you did something that
was using Java and had Java in it you
had to call it Java and and and you
couldn't have a different name. So
that's why initially for instance
Microsoft clashed with them. Uh and then
Microsoft went went went away and and
designed C which was sort of a a Java on
some steroids. They they threw in a bit
more than what Java had at the time. U
the I think the nastiness came Sun was
actually quite an open company. Uh so at
the time we no we were not worried about
that. So that was in the time frame from
1998 to 2004 2005 something like that.
Uh and at the time there was no issue. I
think the issue came later when Sun was
acquired by Oracle and Google forked
Scala on Android Java on Android and
that's when the fight started but that
was much later. So uh when you say that
Scola was using the JVM or built on top
of it um like concretely in the the tech
stack what does it mean that Scola uses
the JVM like how does Java source code
eventually execute on a machine?
>> So the JVM is u essentially defined by
its bite code. So the bite code is
essentially an intermediate format which
you can translate your program into and
then the the bite code is run first by
an interpreter and then essentially by
an optimized compiler just just in time
compiler JIT so that's called JIT they
they they do that and
so if you can if you know how to uh
output bite code and that's not very
hard then you can run on the JVM so So
that's essentially the the idea. The
harder part then is interrupt that you
say okay I run on the JVM. I have to
make sense of all these Java libraries
out there. So I have to somehow map a
Java concept into a Scala concept
[snorts] so that the compiler can
understand what it is and I can document
what it is in for Scala programmers that
maybe don't understand much Java. So so
that that is sort of a work that is sort
of goes more into the details. That
said, I mean that's not the only uh
Scala platform. So it was born on the
JVM, but now it also exists uh on on
JavaScript and NodeJS uh on WAM and and
on native. So it's really a
multiplatform language. OpenAI, [snorts]
Enthropic, Cursor, and Verscell all use
this product to make their lives better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SAS or an AI product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SKIM, there's
arbback, there's audit logs. These are
all things that take time to integrate
but aren't the main focus of your app.
Work OS is an API layer that lets you
meet all of these requirements in just a
few lines of code. So, let's say you
have a new SAS product and you want to
sell to other companies. Work OS will
solve all of these critical feature gaps
for you. You can check them out at
workos.com to learn more and get
started. And I appreciate them for
supporting my work and sponsoring this
podcast. Jira bytassian isn't just for
tracking work anymore. Now you can pick
your favorite AI agent to assign tasks
to and they'll get access to the rich
context that's already in Jira. When the
agent is done, it surfaces pull request.
That way you can get more done with your
favorite agents all in one place. Learn
more at jira.dev. That's jir.dev.
Appreciate them for sponsoring the
podcast. And back to the show. Let's say
I write a Scola program. Uh I have the
source code. I have to compile it and
then I have some Java bite code and then
I call I don't know JVM and I pass in
this bite code and it just works.
>> Yeah. Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
>> What would the advantage be of compiling
Scola to Java byte code instead of doing
something like C and C++ where you
compile it all the way to machine code
from source?
>> We we have that too. And so the Scala
native compiles directly using LLVM to
to native code. Um the advantages of um
compiling to bite code is essentially
again the interrupt can use all the Java
libraries. Then uh the the garbage
collectors. So the the JVM has actually
very good garbage collectors, high
performance ones. Um and um and the
runtime loading. So, so what what I can
do on the JVM is I can compile let's say
a oneline thing into a little Java bite
code and I can immediately load that by
code and execute that and that makes it
very easy for instance to have a ripple
because that's how how how a ripple
would work a redevelop print loop so I
would just generate a snippet of Scala
code to bite code load it into the
running JVM process and it gets executed
and that's much harder if you go to
binaries basically the binary ers don't
really have a concept for that.
>> You mentioned that you wrote a compiler
for Java like before Scola and I I've
heard that compilers are notoriously
hard to build. Um can you explain the
hard parts and why they're hard?
>> Compilers are
very intricate. Um because uh I think
there there a lot of requirements on a
compiler. So you have languages which
are already complex artifacts. Uh then
you have a thing called type inference.
So you have a type system but
essentially you demand the compiler to
essentially infer a lot of types that
make sense because you as a programmer
thinks well the compiler should know
that and it should uh but actually to
for the compiler to do that is is quite
hard. And then then you of course you
also demand that it would would would
generate very efficient code for your
program because again the compiler
should know that right so there's a lot
of demands on that plus there's a demand
that it should should be very very fast
uh and to square all these demands
requires quite a bit of work basically
there are also things that make it
easier for compilers because they're
fundamentally deterministic programs. So
essentially you run a compiler on a
source and you should you always get the
same output. So it means they're easier
to debug. You can just replay things and
repeat things. Whereas if I would have
some cloud service or distributed
application that has other nightmares,
right? That every run is different and
how how do you even figure out what goes
wrong?
>> So when you wrote that compiler uh I
think espresso for Java um how long did
it take to write that by hand? uh at the
time it took me about 3 months I think
not full-time maybe half time three
months half time something like that but
that was a very simple compiler too so
that's the other thing with compilers
they typically start simple and when
you're at the 10 year mark or 20 year
mark then there's lots and lots of
essentially other requirements to a
compiler that make them more complex.
Were there libraries that you could rely
on to to kind of piece together
components of it or did you have to
write you know everything from scratch?
I wrote there was a library to uh
generate uh bite codes I think uh I
think I used that in that version. Yeah
I did. Yeah. So there was a a library
that essentially a high level library to
just assemble by codes and and put them
in the to the right format and things
like that. Uh but that was essentially
it. The rest I wrote by hand. Yeah.
That's crazy because well I mean these
days a lot of people even more so now
we're thinking less using AI more to
kind of you know write the code. So
that's pretty impressive. I saw one of
the big I guess moments for Scola was
that Twitter adopted it and I wanted to
know the story behind that. How did they
choose such a obscure language at that
time?
>> It was very obscure at the time. That's
true. Uh so I believe the story was
Twitter originally was written in Ruby
and um it wasn't very reliable because I
believe it's again a problem with
garbage collector and memory management
and things like that. So uh the uh and
it was a small company at the time. So
25 people uh including the ops people
and um the uh essentially the the board
and the VC investors said you can't go
on like this being unreliable like that.
You should do Java because Java was sort
of the solid choice at the time. But the
the the some some of the engineers at at
Twitter they wanted essentially
something more fancy as a programming
language and there were some people who
knew Okamo and liked Okamo but of course
Okamel didn't run on the JVM and then
they found Scala and said well Scala is
actually quite a lot like Okamo and we
can tell our investors that we do Java
because it's not a lie we do JVM JVM by
code that's essentially what it what
what where what it comes down to. So
that's why why they picked it and they
were quite the first but once they
picked it sort of the floodgates opened
because at that time they were very uh
interesting company and a lot of people
admired them. So a lot of people
followed and did the same thing then uh
mostly they came from dynamic languages.
So Twitter came from Ruby others came
from PHP or uh yeah JavaScript uh things
like that. I mentioned a little bit that
you know AI is kind of generating a lot
of code and I wanted to ask you what you
thought maybe the future of programming
languages might look like if you kind of
speculated or drew out further into the
future like if AI is generating more of
the code. How do you think that might
affect the programming language
ecosystem?
>> Yeah, I think right now we are sort of
in an existential crisis, right? So we
have [snorts] AI generating the code but
uh uh humans being asked impossible
tasks like to review all this these
mountains of code and things like that
which will never work. Um and uh at the
same time a AI is also gotten extremely
good at exploiting vulnerabilities in
code like we we all heard of Fable and
and and things like that that you can't
use it anymore because it's too
dangerous. It will exploit things. So
um we are at a moment where it's
essentially very dangerous that we lose
control as humans of what what actually
happens here and uh that's a challenge
that I think programming languages can
help meet and probably definitely not
only programming languages that's no
silver bullet but they definitely can
help things. Um so I think one of the
things is that the focus if the code is
AI generated then the focus has to go
elsewhere and I think the co focus will
go to the interfaces and to the types.
So I expect types will become a lot
stronger and more precise than than what
we had because types is essentially the
handle that we can make a contract
between the human and the AI that the
that the human can understand and that's
concise enough to be reviewed and that
essentially the AI can keep to uh we
have to level our game quite a lot. Uh
because right now I mean let's face it
type systems are mostly
um uh recommendations. Uh they're mostly
uh things that uh mostly hold but not
always. There are no guarantees because
you can always have a cast or well you
you use some dirty memory or I mean
there there are number of a lot of
techniques to sort of undermine the type
systems and we have to close all these
holes from the beginning because uh once
once there is a hole somebody can
exploit it. Uh so I think strong types
strong highle types will help. Um and
then I think the the other part is
generally the programmer has to think
much more about what are the
requirements and what are the
essentially the high level
specifications
uh and be able to leave the code to be
generated by somebody else in confidence
and uh I think we're not quite there yet
but we we we have some ideas how we
could get there. uh so one one uh
technique that I believe uh we can use
and it has been around for a long time
but maybe it's time has come now this
capabilities capabilities essent
essentially was used in operating
systems to give very fine grain
permissions to to uh entities users
programs and things like that and uh I
believe that can be used also for agents
and the agentic AI to say well once we
have agents We have to give agents very
precise and fine grain capabilities what
they can do and that lets us essentially
be confident about what they will not be
able to do like they will not be able to
leak my API keys or my email or or do do
other things right so I think that's
that's an important part uh and the
existing languages are uh not there yet
uh I think Scala is halfway there at
least it's there where in essentially
stuff we're working on which we have in
the lab and we have released as an
experimental feature. So I'm quite
excited about that. Um the first thing
that you have to do is definitely be
memory safe. So a language that
essentially is is not safe in memory
that lets you essentially uh access
undefined memory uh is immediately out
because you can't you can't guarantee
anything. So that's in that sense it's
good that there is a drive to use let's
say rust as a memory safe language we're
even that that was even promoted by the
American government I believe so that's
definitely a very useful drive but I
think you need a lot more because you
need much rest talk folks essentially
mostly or only about memory you need to
talk about a lot more things than memory
you need about essentially read
permissions write permissions access to
secrets all these things that that are
that are uh uh that go beyond that and u
you could say okay uh that
Martin you're totally unrealistic
because uh all our software is written
in C and C++ and we will not be able to
rewrite that uh but that I believe AIS
can help there right so AIs are great to
re in rewriting software so if we know
what to rewrite too I think we could we
might be able to get there
>> you mentioned some of those experimental
features in Scola that um might have
some sort of safety guarantees or signal
capabilities. Can you explain what that
might look like or maybe give an
example?
>> So, so a simple example would would be
let's say somebody gives me a file and
um uh and uh I have access to the file
let's say a log file or something like
that. I have access for a file for a
limited time and then I I need to close
it. So typically I have a operation that
essentially somebody passes I a file to
me to an operation that my program
provides and the program does something
with the file and then the environment
will close it. But how do we make sure
that I don't hold on to the file after I
get it back to the environment or after
I I I pretended I'm finished with it
because hey I I have a file. I could
have stored it in a variable. I could
have stored it on the side. I could have
gone g come g come g come g come g come
g come g come g come g come g come g
come g come g come g come g come g come
g come g come g come g come comeone back
to it and done something with it. So uh
capabilities help me prevent that
because essentially I I can say okay so
this file is a capability and then I can
further say well this capability can be
used only in a limited scope and the
type system will make sure that the
capability doesn't escape and the way we
do that is that if a type refers to
capabilities so if I have a a thing that
I say I give you back a a lambda or a a
stream and it holds on to the file. So
the stream holds on to the file in
secret. In our language that won't be a
secret anymore because the type has to
declare that the thing I return does
hold on to the file. The file is a
capability and I can't essentially hide
capabilities I have access to in my
type. I have to be I have to declare
them and that gives me essentially this
this control that then I can also
enforce to say well at this point you're
not allowed to have any capability
because the type that I enforced you to
have is a type that doesn't hold
capabilities and that's that way I
enforce with the type system something
which uh previously hasn't really been
enforcable
uh with for memory safety it's
essentially the same thing with arenas
uh that I I have an area where I
allocate memory and then I want want to
get rid of it. I have to make sure I
don't have pointers pointing into it and
that's exactly the same the same
situation and and let's say for
accessing secrets again. So it's a very
common pattern that I say in certain
situations I want to make sure that you
don't have uh or that you only have a
set of defined capabilities that I give
you and nothing else. You mentioned uh
memory safety is an absolute uh table
stakes. What are the programming
languages that you think of that are not
memory safe? I know there's C, but what
are the other ones?
>> The big ones is C, C++. Um I I don't
know about I think Zik or Nim or other
low-level systems languages are not
memory safe. So that was sort of in Rust
the a big achievement that you say you
can be a low-level systems languages and
be be memory safe. nobody sort of
thought that that was possible before
Rust came. Uh so so that's why I would
think I don't want to say anything wrong
but I would think that essentially most
other low-level systems languages would
not be memory safe. Um but you really
need more than memory safe. You really
need capability safes that you say you
when I essentially hang on tell you I
can't sort of forget capabilities to say
I hang on to something and I I just
conveniently forget that I have access
to that and I can't forge capabilities
to say well if I need a capability I
just make one up. And so these two
things need to be prevented and that
goes go that goes beyond memory safety.
But memory safety without memory safety
essentially you have nothing because you
can fake everything.
>> A lot of programming language design and
how we write code in the past is writing
the source code so that it's um it's
it's nice for humans to read. But if
humans are no longer interacting with
the code, what kind of things come to
mind that we might not care as much
about but are good for machines to read.
For instance,
>> the first thing is uh maybe sometimes
you want to read it uh but you probably
wouldn't have written it. So easy to
write is definitely not not a big
criterion anymore. Easy to read to some
degree. Yes. But that means you don't
need any these these sort of syntactic
hacks like to write plus+ in C or things
like that that's easy to write right. So
but I I don't I mean I'm sure we will
still have that but it doesn't really
matter anymore. I mean whether [snorts]
I write an assignment in in long form or
with X++ whatever. So I think these
things won't won't matter much less. the
things that matter much more are or that
continue to matter and uh are
essentially high level ways to constrain
and specify what my program should do.
So uh constrain what it should not do.
Uh that's that's one of the things and
also specify what it should do. uh and I
mean some people say it's a golden age
for formal verification because we can
be very precise in our specifications
and our AI can actually not just finish
the program but also the proof that the
that the program actually meets the
specification and I think that's true
that's really very exciting in in in a
lot of areas but in the large uh the
problem is you often don't really have
the formal specification or it's just as
hard to write a formal specific
ification than to write a program or
sometimes even harder. So that means
that we will still have live in a world
where we specify things by natural
languages by prompt to the agent and and
the agent then will will do the code.
But I imagine that also the that will be
a lot more
um formal in a way. So, so in a sense
right now the prompts I mean it's
fantastic what they can do with the
prompts but then we throw away the
prompt or the it's hidden in in the chat
history with the agent. So that's really
a shame. So I really should should have
the prompts as first class values in my
program that I can say well essentially
that's what the program is about and if
I change the prompt then the AI will
know essentially what the incremental
change was and change the program
incrementally. these sort of things.
That's another thing that I think we'll
see in future programming languages for
a agentic programming.
>> Maybe like some kind of meta meta
information about the program almost
like a git blame but like a you know
prompt I guess blame of what generated
that that part of the code.
>> You should be able to to to keep that
around and and come back to it. Yeah.
Also because you want you might want to
change, right? You might want to say
well now it's exactly the same but I
want to change this little detail but I
don't want the LLM nondeterministically
to generate a new program because that
way well it might get a lot of other
things wrong that I reviewed already. So
there really should then be an
incremental small change to the code and
that means I keep I need to keep the
prompt as a part of my program.
>> 10 years from now do you think there
will be more software engineers than
today or less?
I think there will be less uh the
uh and it will be a higher um
profession that is essentially has
higher standards. Uh so it will be
harder to become one. You will know be
able to know quite a lot of logics and
maths to be competent at essentially
keeping AI on the good track and things
like that. It's sort of can say it's
sort of like a like a control engineer
for a factory where you don't understand
many things in initially. It means that
there must be more you must be higher
skilled than a a factory worker of uh 50
years ago or something like that and I
think the same will will happen for
software where you will need fewer but
more qualified people. One thing that a
lot of people recommend is to become
better at programming you should learn
multiple languages and I wanted to know
aside from Scola what are the top
programming languages you would
recommend people learn to expand their
mind. So definitely a systems language
uh I think to to know how how how
hardware works and how software links
with hardware I would learn a systems
language and um
I'm sort of torn between C and Rust
there because C has going for it that
it's very simple and very close to a
thing in Rust you have to learn a lot of
abstractions but on the other hand it is
memory safe so I would say probably
initially see to figure out what these
things are and then if If you decide to
become a systems programmer as a career
then you should switch to rest I guess.
So that would be one thing. Uh the other
thing would be something more
uh with a verification improving
background because that will be a lot
more will become a lot more important.
So I would actually do a course in in
lean or or rock or one of these
languages uh to say where we we should
be able to use AI or to to to have to
develop first an intuition what it means
for a program to be correct because I
guess for most people have only a very
very uh fuzzy fuzzy intuition for these
things and and learning one of these
languages would sharpen the mind.
Um yeah, so I think those and then of
course Scala too as a language that
essentially sits right in the middle
where fairly fairly provable strong
types uh high expressivity these sort of
things.
>> Yeah. When you think of a top technical
book that you might recommend people
does anything come to mind?
>> I got a lot out of uh structure and
interpretation of computer programs that
was a book from the '9s. It was the
intro text at MIT at the time uh or 80s
even I think um and in fact this the
courses I taught on Corera and and uh at
DPFL are based quite a lot well to some
degree they're based based on that
material. So of course not the same
language and strong types instead of
dynamically type but still
>> when you look back on your career why
did you choose to work in academia
instead of industry? When I came to the
end of my studies, I uh was asked to do
a research project and the project I
picked or the prof then asked from me to
modulate that a little bit. In the end,
I found it super interesting to say I I
work on something that I don't know
whether it has a solution or not. Uh so
uh it it might be that uh the question
is yes, it might be the question is no.
We have to do research and that's sort
of how it started. And then
then I I believe the the main advantage
of uh being in academia is really the
long term and being independent. So in
the long term I mean ind in industry I'm
sure there are many periods including
now where I could be paid 10 times what
I'm being paid at university if I joined
Google or any of the other companies in
Silicon Valley. But um then times also
change and sometimes essentially what
you do is no longer relevant and then
it's very easy to get fired and to
then you say no big deal I can do
something else but at a university you
have essentially long-term tenure to do
exactly what you want. So no manager you
can do define your own research agenda.
Of course you have to get some money
that that that is uh is hard. You have
to get grants and things like that. you
have to convince students that what you
do is uh is the right thing and but
that's also very rewarding working with
students. So I think I in in the end I'm
I'm very happy that I took the career I
took.
>> What about looking back on Scola? Um you
know do you have so much experience
there. What are some things that went
well or things that didn't go well and
maybe some learnings you could share?
Scala was initially this experiment that
we could uh combine object-oriented and
functional programming and technically
that experiment was a big success uh um
in terms of the ecosystem it had a lot
of challenges. I don't know whether you
know there was a there was a short
incomplete history of programming
languages by James Ivy which is quite
hilarious and there was there's a
scholar entry there that this says I
discovered reef spell sandwiches and I
had an idea to essentially have a
language where you put in both object
and functional and then it ends with
this pieces of both communities and
they're promptly declared jihad and
that's [laughter] at the at the
beginning it was very funny but uh in
retrospect That's to a large degree what
happened. I mean there was there were
there were a lot of fights and cultural
fights and things like that. So um and
um
we might have uh it was a challenge and
I don't know in retrospect I think it
might have been
more prudent to be more careful
introducing functional features because
that sort of was we went in uh
essentially
quite complete. So essentially you can
port most Haskell programs to Scala
maybe that you you find them a bit less
attractive looking but you can do it and
that was that brought in essentially
different cultures very
and it caused a big clash of cultures.
So uh for instance in go Go was a lot
maligned because they didn't even have
generics right and it's it's true it was
a ridiculous language but uh by not
having it initially you sort of form a
culture that when you add it nothing
much will go wrong and people won't
overabstract or things like that and by
essentially going full hog into into it
with Scala from the start we were not
protected against that and people did uh
reach abstraction peaks and over
abstract it and and things like that and
that's they still do it to this very
day. So essentially having fancy
abstractions is great but you have to
use them responsibly and uh that then it
sort of clashes with the natural urge to
just try out all these fancy things and
do do something that in the end maybe
neither no you nor understands very well
and it could have just been a simple map
or things like that but uh yeah why do
use that when it can be complicated? Why
would that upset someone?
>> Because of the library ecosystem. I
think that um
um the
so libraries are are important and
because they sort of set the agenda how
you express your programs and in
particular the the uh the libraries that
come from the Haskell side. They're
essentially monatic frameworks and they
require you to express your whole
program as a monot which is a concept
that works well in functional
programming. I have my reservations. I
wouldn't actually do that in my in my
scholar programs, but by having
prominent libraries out there, uh it's
quite normative that people feel like
they they're being a [snorts] scholar
programmer, they're required to program
this way. And then of course there are
opinion leaders and conferences and all
these things that uh tell you how how
you should be writing your programs
where I would say I I think the most of
the scholar community is actually very
very levelheaded and and and and and I I
think most of the advice is great but uh
then um yeah uh it's it's still a
challenge because it's just too easy to
to mostly it's not really the opinion
leaders is in the in the community. But
let's say it's your boss. You have a
small team in a in a company. Your boss
came from Haskell and says, "Hey, this
is great. We do exactly like Haskell.
The whole thing." And then two years
later, the boss's boss says, "No, nobody
can understand this code. This code and
the project is canled." So these things
happened in in in in the industry. Uh
I'm not saying that they they that all
projects are like that. Not at all. I
mean there are lots of really great
success stories of Scala but that's
essentially a challenge in terms of
tech. Um I I think in the end um I wish
we had been a bit less dependent on the
JVM u uh in the sense that we took a lot
from Java that intuitively makes sense
but in the end and and was very
important for interrupt but in the end
wasn't wasn't
could have been done better. So for
instance uh in in Java being an object-
oriented language you have universal
methods like tworing and equals and hash
code and they're defined for everything
and languages like Rust or or Haskell
there are no more more discriminating.
They have a thing called type classes
where essentially you at compile time
you tell exactly where you have equality
and and hash code and these things and
it's a bit more tedious to set these
things up but it it in the end it's also
safer. So I wish we had that and and we
did we couldn't because we sort of
adapted Java's notion of what what an
object is and it already came with all
these things which is sort of very
convenient but in the end uh caused
friction. If I went back to you at that
time when you were starting it, I said,
"What do you think's going to happen 20
years from now?" What would you have
said?
>> I would probably have said that uh well,
it was a footnote in memory. Uh uh
because I mean, let's face it, you you
do a you do a thing and initially we had
maybe five users or something like that
outside our group, some something like
that, right? So, so and you don't really
expect that it would change a lot. Uh
and so I don't know I think it was was
quite quite by surprise that this
actually happened. Uh
and um I think the reason why it
happened was that at the [clears throat]
time
um Scala was a good
bridge between dynamic languages that
are slow and sometimes they crash and
solid languages, statically typed
languages like Java uh which were at the
time quite cumbersome to write code and
there was a lot of ceremony and things
like that and and Scola to the inferred
types. So you had types but you didn't
see them much. So it felt like a dynamic
language. Uh but it had also the
solidity of essentially a good platform.
And I think that's what made it. And
we've we've been copied a lot by a lot
of other languages that put in in these
features then five or 10 years later or
things like that. But at the time it was
sort of scala that that was the first
one that had it and that's sort of why
it happened. Um but um I wouldn't have
foreseen that by no means.
>> Looking back on your career uh when you
just graduated college and kind of
started your career um knowing what you
know today what advice would you give
your younger self?
>> I I think to take risks be adventurous
paid pay it out. So essentially don't
follow
the the mainstream. Uh if if you take a
fancy to do something wild uh and crazy
technically take the time to do it and
do it. Um uh but I mean yeah so that's
what I would of course I mean you still
need to sort of stay on track somewhat
but uh I don't want to you to exaggerate
that either but [laughter] but yeah so
so basically be a bit non-confirmist.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, professor. I really
appreciate it.
>> Thank you, Ryan.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within 8
hours of launching. I really appreciate
it if you were one of the people who
grabbed one of the early units. Um,
we're now working on the long journey of
building the tooling now. So, if you
still want to pick one up, I've left the
late pledges open on Kickstarter, so you
can grab one there. I'll put a link in
the description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast and I'll see you in
the next